Mazel Tov מזל טוב Mazel Tov everybody, today's daf דף daf is
Samech Hey סה, Samech Hey, Chodesh Tov חודש טוב, Chodesh Tov, only
two weeks to Pesach פסח. Pesach. Don't worry you got plenty of
time, plenty of time. Okay anyway we pick up with the Mishna
משנה Mishna at the bottom of Samech Hey סה Samech Hey Amud
Alef עמוד א Amud Alef or a little bit ahead. We're continuing
to discuss when you sell certain property what's considered to be included
with it and we've been discussing like selling the house and do
you get like the well which now we've discovered is within the
house and interestingly even though it's the water supply you don't get
the well you know do you get like the other types of
things but now we get to what I think for us people
particularly those who rent apartments or whatever is the standard question which
is furnished or unfurnished. Okay so that's for us more of a
question when you rent but it's also a question when you buy
the house. Okay I'm selling you my house so by the way
I'm taking my fridge and my stove with me you know do
you say that can you say that or not? So let's take
a look at this. I tell you when I rented the well
let's take a look let's look at the Mishna משנה. Mishna. Hamocher
es Habayis המוכר את הבית Hamocher es Habayis somebody sells a house,
Machar es Hadeles מכר את הדלת. Machar es Hadeles. Oh you don't
get to take the door with you fine take the house I'm
taking the door. No the door goes with the house it's attached.
Can you imagine if the keeper wanted to take if they really
wanted to take the door? I don't think so I think that's
implicit in the sale. At the moment of sale if you're selling
the house it means everything that currently is attached to the house.
You also can't tear down the house and replace it with different
building materials either. Okay so Machar es Hadeles מכר את הדלת Machar
es Hadeles but not it's not like the Mezuzah מזוזה Mezuzah question
this is considered a part of the house. Okay Aval lo es
Hamafteach אבל לא את המפתח. Aval lo es Hamafteach. Now Mafteach מפתח
Mafteach normally means the key of course yeah of course if it's
a key it's like specific to that lock and what are you
doing going around with that key? It probably means something more like
a bolt like or like a bolt you know a bolt that
would fit into the locking mechanism that could be removed. So I'm
going to use this bolt for my house so and therefore you
can remove it and go ahead and take it with you. You'd
have to be like a lock basically right? Yeah but these are
things but part of the point here is that these are things
that are not attached. The main dividing line is going to be
whether they are physically attached or not. So if it's a lock
you cannot unscrew the lock on your door and take it with
you. Wait isn't it easy to assume that you actually do take
the lock? Oh because people are going to want to yeah they
don't trust you to keep the original key. That's true but that's
for a different reason but that's true. But the basic rule here
is that it goes by what is attached as opposed to what
is not attached. Okay. Machar es Hamachteshes מכר את המכתשת Machar es
Hamachteshes Kavuah קבועה Kavuah but not the Mitataltelt מטלטלת Mitataltelt and that's
made even more explicit here. So you have a mortar something you
use for grinding spices so you could have one that is basically
like built into the wall okay I guess that means or I
mean well actually what's the base? I keep on getting the base
is the mortar and the top is the pestle? I think so.
So anyway okay so or the mortar is attached to the ground.
Right right so it's attached I mean I give an example the
wall because I just imagined it harder by the ground unless you're
doing a lot of spices maybe and you've got like a major
industrial one. Right right right something like that. Anyway so if it
is somehow physically attached to the wall or to the ground then
that's part of the house if however it is not if it's
a movable one then you take that with you. Machar es Ha'itztrubel
מכר את האיצטרובל Machar es Ha'itztrubel you sell the Itztrubel איצטרובל Itztrubel
which has got to be a Greek word which is basically some
type of a frame for a millstone so again something that is
physically attached to the floor of the house. Aval lo es Hakeles
אבל לא את הקלת Aval lo es Hakeles but not the Keles
קלת Keles which is either like the sieve or the funnel that
you use for pouring the wheat into the mill. So that is
something that is more detachable. Is that a millstone or just a
funnel? I mean like it's not built in. Yeah but it's a
funnel made for this mill. Maybe it's custom made? I don't know
if it's custom it might be standard size but if I'm leaving
behind the frame for the mill maybe I leave behind the pieces
that go with it you know? Everything seems to be custom made
no? Right that's true
yeah that is true. It still might have they still might have
had standard sizes but yes. Okay. Can they take the pestle like
you know the mortar? Yeah that's interesting I was wondering about that
you leave behind the mortar do you take the pestle with you?
Right because they didn't mention the Keles קלת. Keles. Right presumably you
would you know? Because it's a separate piece? Yeah I don't know
it's a good question I don't know. Velo es Hatanur Velo es
Hakirayim ולא את התנור ולא את הכיריים. Velo es Hatanur Velo es
Hakirayim. Not the oven and not the stove. Those are not sold
those you do take with you and these are things that also
are not necessarily attached to the ground. There's actually an interesting debate
of the Rashbam רשב"ם Rashbam and Tosafot תוספות Tosafot or two opinions
in Tosafot תוספות Tosafot that sometimes they actually would plaster them to
the ground but the plastering would not necessarily be as like a
permanent attachment. Even when they would be plastered you know it's to
stabilize them or whatever but you would often but you know it
would not be unusual for you to break the plaster and move
it somewhere else. So these things are not considered to be like
really they're either not attached at all or not really attached in
a serious way and therefore that is the basic rule only things
that are attached. Okay. בזמן שאמר לו היא וכל מה שבתוכה, Bizman
she'amar lo hi vechol mah shebetochah,
but if the document said I'm selling it to you with all
of its contents, הרי כולן מכורין, Harei kulan mekhurin, they're all sold.
Now you might think that's obvious, but actually, it's not so obvious,
because "all of its contents" still has a narrow meaning. It means
these types of things which are generally used in the, like you
know, like the standard types of furnishing. If I say all of
its contents, I don't mean my wallet that I left, accidentally left
in my bedroom. Oh, it says all of the contents, so you
sold me your wallet, right? You know, so it would only be
these are the types of things which you would sort of say
as like what a standard like furnishings of the house would be.
Those would be sold. Now you're teaching me something. Yeah, not your—exactly.
So if what exactly is the line, you could look at the
Rashbam. So let's look at the Rashbam here. הרי כולן מכורין. Harei
kulan mekhurin. כל הנך תשמישין המטלטלין. Kol hanach tashmishin hamitaltelin. תשמישין. Tashmishin.
All these things that are basically used together, you know, even though
they're movable, but they're considered to be like the usages of the
home. Okay. אבל שאר מיני תשמישתיה לא מיזדבני. Aval shear minei tashmishtei
lo mizdabnei. ואף על גב דאמר "כל מה שבתוכה אני מוכר לך",
Ve'af al gav de'amar "kol mah shebetochah ani mocher lach", I'm selling
you everything, שלא ריבה בלשון זה אלא תשמישין המיוחדים לבית זה. Shelo
ribah bilshon ze ela tashmishin hamyuchadim labayit ze.
Things that are like not only that they normally go, you know,
so-to-speak, are going with the house, but they go with this house,
as opposed to—and his way of sort of testing this is—שאינן רגילים
להשאילם מפני כבידן. She'einan regilim lehash'ilam mipnei kveidan. What,
if you came to me and you asked like, "Can I borrow
your ax," right? So would I normally like lend them out or
not? And things that I would not normally lend them out—they're too
heavy, they're whatever, they're things I keep in the house regularly, I
wouldn't normally lend them out—those are things that are seen to like
go with the house.
So
he's
saying still not
including the kitchen table,
but
you
wouldn't lend out
a kitchen table.
Right, I understand, but according to what he's saying, the kitchen table—so
it's not always able to know exactly what the line is. How
about chairs, right? Chairs, I would think would be more likely wouldn't
be sold. I don't know, it's hard to know the line. I
mean, I would tell you again, this is what I was referring
to before, you know, when we rented our apartment—not rented, we bought
our apartment—and we bought it in, you know, whatever, we bought it
like in the middle of the summer, and then we came in
and we realized that, I don't know, maybe we were informed about
this, doesn't matter, anyway, we came in and they took all the
air conditioners. You know,
so it's like, and there we were, we were like, "Oh my
God," so shvitzing there that first night. Anyway, you know, that's something—it's
very heavy, right? And it would be something you would think would
go with the apartment as part of the normal heating of the
apartment. Anyway, but I think isn't there a rule now in New
York City or something that you have to leave air conditioners behind?
I don't know.
Yeah, anyway, what?
Yeah, but you can—you can remove them. They're like—it's not built-in, it's
not totally built-in. You can—anyway. All right, moving on. So that—but it
is interesting to figure out what that line is. So when you
don't specify, it's things that are attached. When you do—you don't say
"kol shebetocha," when you do say "kol shebetocha," they don't have to
be attached, but they have to be somehow seen as connected in
some, you know,
you know, in some serious way to the house. Okay.
And then he says—the Gemara says—different reasons. Let's go on, let's look
at the Gemara. לימא מתניתין דלא כרבי מאיר. Leima matnitin dlo k'Rabbi
Meir. Let's say our Mishna, that exactly this, that focuses just on
whether it's physically attached and not on when it's like something that's
standard used together with it, is not like Rabbi Meir, because Rabbi
Meir more looks at not attached versus not attached, but whether it's
standardly used together. דאי רבי מאיר אמר מכר את הכרם מכר תשמישי
כרם. De'ei Rabbi Meir amar machar et hakarem machar tashmishei karem. If
I'm selling Michael here my vineyard,
then not only do I sell him the vineyard, I sell him
also like the sticks and the frames and all that stuff that
goes with it, even the stuff that's not physically attached to the
ground. But that's the stuff that's, you know, it's the equipment that
goes with it. So we should say the same by the house,
like exactly the standard sort of associated equipment of the house, even
if it's not physically attached. So Mishna says, no. אפילו תימא רבי
מאיר. Afilu teima Rabbi Meir. It could even go like Rabbi Meir.
התם קביעה הכא לא קביעה. Hatam kvia hacha lo kvia. There, by
the vineyard, even if it's not attached, okay, that's still something that's...
The way the רשב״ם *Rashbam* says you never remove, like take those
frames and put them somewhere else. Meaning that they're there. They're there
already. Even if you didn't put them there, you don't have to...
Yeah, yeah, yeah. We're not talking about. So but those are the
things that like are permanently stay there even if they're not physically
attached as opposed to the types of things in our משנה mishna,
*mishna* even if like conceptually, you know, the mortar and the pestle
that isn't attached is something that goes with the house, it's not
like you always leave it there. Like it's something that you could
in theory at least, you know, maybe sometimes remove. Again it's hard
to know the exact line because the רשב״ם *Rashbam* a minute ago
said that actually those are the things that you don't normally lend
out, okay? But anyway the גמרא gemara *Gemara* is trying to make
a distinction that maybe it's not you're right, רבי מאיר *Rebbe Meir*
doesn't need attached but he needs something that has some more permanent
association. And the things in our משנה mishna *mishna* that are not
attached are not in some deep way permanently associated. So the גמרא
gemara *Gemara* says one minute, והמפתח דומיא דדלת קתני *V'hamafteach dumya d'deles
katani* but we said that you don't sell the door and you
do sell the bolt, let's say מפתח *mafteach* means the bolt. מה
דלת דקביעה אף מפתח דקביעה *Ma deles dekvia af mafteach dekvia*. So
presumably we mean a bolt which is just as associated to the
house as the door and the only difference is that one is
attached and one isn't attached. So we must be referring to even
a case of a bolt that is only used together with the
house and even so it is not sold. As the way the
רשב״ם *Rashbam* says it is that if we really were going to
distinguish between two types, two types of bolts, that would have been
more interesting than distinguishing between a bolt and a door. We should
have said a bolt that is only used with this house is
sold and a bolt that isn't used only, isn't limited to this
house isn't sold. So the fact that we draw the line between
the bolt and the door and not between two types of bolts
indicate that all bolts would not be sold even those that have
a very fixed use together with this house. So אף מפתח דקביעה
*Af mafteach dekvia* so even if it's a type of a bolt
that is fixed and generally used, you know, only really used together
with this house, as long as it's not physically attached it's not
sold. אלא מחוורתא מתניתין דלא כרבי מאיר *Ela machvarta masnisin d'lo k'Rebbe
Meir*. So you're right, it says the משנה mishna, *mishna* isn't רבי
מאיר *Rebbe Meir*. In our משנה Mishna. *mishna* it does not matter
how much something's use is directly sort of fixed together with the
house as long as it's not physically attached it would not be
sold. Okay so that is the line in our משנה Mishnah: *mishna*
and that's not רבי מאיר *Rebbe Meir* which is an easier test,
it's easier right to just say is it physically attached or not
physically attached? Okay once you start conceptualizing it, something that has a
fixed use together with it, always goes together with it, you don't
lend out, well that's the types of things the רשב״ם *Rashbam* said
would be included if you said everything, all of its contents, then
you can, we have all these debates. Does that mean the kitchen
table or not mean the kitchen table? Does that mean the sofa
or not mean the sofa, right? So then it's more but at
least within the משנה *mishna* the line is clear, physically attached or
not physically attached. And you're assuming מפתח *mafteach* means bolt, because it
doesn't make sense... Yeah, that's what the, that's what the Soncino said.
Soncino translated it as, because a key, like it could be a
key that's just a normal type of a, you know, like a
universal key. Like it's a lock and like any type of a
key. So it could mean that. Why is that what you, you're,
I saw you guys having a little conference here. It says right
here, literally translated as key. As a key. Soncino translated it as
a, as a bolt. He wanted to understand something more that you
would want to bring, like from one place to the next. But
you could understand like a universal key that the lock is not
so much a safety lock, a security lock, it's more like a
handle, right? And then if you have the key, you know, it's
just, it's not, you know, you just like it's a way of
just opening or closing the... Right. I was mostly asking because there's
a specific word for bolt which is נגרא *nagara* which actually we're
going to get to. Yeah, I know. בריח *bariach* and נגרא *nagara*...
בריח *bariach* we're going to get to some of that later, right.
Okay. So, yeah, yeah, yeah. And that's the Soncino translation but it
could be a key but you have to understand that it's some
key that's not unique to this particular lock. Otherwise it would be
like exactly as the... Exactly. Well, unless that's what the גמרא Gemara
*Gemara* means that the fact that it says, that it says מפתח
דקביעה *mafteach dekvia* means that maybe it is a key that only
fits this lock and even so it's not sold. I'm thinking maybe
from the inside, anyway, one of those types of keys that... the
key also was like fixed... Maybe. Oh, the key was something used
on the inside of the door not the outside of the door.
Could be. Yeah, I don't know enough of this. Okay. תנו רבנן
Tanu rabanan. המוכר את הבית מוכר את הדלת ואת הנגר ואת המנעול
*Tanu rabanan hamocher es habayis mocher es hadeles v'es hanagar v'es hamanul*.
Okay, so here you go, here are things that... מנעול *manul*, I'm
sorry, מנעול *manul*. Okay, so נגר *nagar* is actually the רשב״ם *Rashbam*
says that is like a type of a bolt but I understood
him to mean more like a, not like a, like a larger
bolt like one that goes sort of across בריח *bariach* he says
like goes across the whole width of the door, not just like
you know in that gap between the door and the door frame.
Okay and and they say it's attached to the wall actually, it's
across...
Right,
because these are things that you are... right, thank you for clarifying.
Right. I was going to get to that. These are things that
are sold together. So this is a type of an attached bolt
and a מנעול *manul* is the actual, is the actual lock itself
because these, all these are things that are attached. אבל לא את
המפתח *Aval lo es hamafteach*. but not the I guess we'll call
it now key. מכתת המכתשת החקוקה, אבל לא
את הקבועה. aval lo et hakvua. You sold the mortar that is
carved into the wall,
but, you know, imagine, I don't know, you had some protrusion from
the wall and you actually like a stone that was protruding and
you carved a,
you know, like a concave thing, right? Niche, like a niche.
Yeah, I mean, basically, right, if this is your wall, right, and
you had some stone protruding out from here and you carved something
in there. Now you can use that as a...
well, oh, because קבועה kvua means that means that it was separate
and then you attached it, okay? So it's חקוקה chakuka if it
was directly dug into the wall, then it's sold, okay? But if
you basically, if you look at the רשב"ם, Rashbam, and this is
actually what we're going to be focusing on in a minute, he
says אבל לא את הקבועה, aval lo et hakvua, he says שהייתה
חקוקה ועשויה ואחר כך קבע בקרקע. shehayta chakuka veasuya veachar kach kava
bekarka. Okay, now, so it was separate and then you attached it.
Now in our משנה, it seems like things that were separate and
attached like would be considered part of the structure, right? Because our
משנה for example had the מכתשת הקבועה, machteshet hakvua, which is exactly...
but anyway, but now we're going to get into a really... this
is going to soon be the focus and it's not going to
be limited to a question of what's included in the house but
a more broad conceptual question which is, how do you think about
something that existed as a כלי, kli, as a type of a
vessel, you know, when it was unattached and then it was affixed
to the ground or affixed to the structure? Is it considered like
something that is like attached to the ground or is it considered
something that is a כלי? kli? It could be even related to
טומאה. tumah.
Exactly, there's a lot of relevance to that. Okay, so anyway, but
this ברייתא braita seems to, you know, if that's the line between
it, so then if it was separate and then attached as opposed
to dug right in, then it would not be considered part of
the house and actually you would detach it and take it with
you.
Okay, אבל לא
את הקבועה. aval lo et hakvua. מכר את האיצטרובלה אבל לא את
הקלת. machar et haitztrobela aval lo et hakelet. Again, you sold the
frame for the millstone but not the sieve or the funnel.
לא את התנור ולא את הכיראיים, lo et hatannur velo et hakirayim,
and not the oven and not the stove. ולא את הריחיים velo
et harechayim and not actually the millstone itself. That's also, you know,
movable. You take the millstone with you. I know, there's a lot
of טרחא. tircha. I know, those are big. And the רשב"ם Rashbam
on the previous page makes a whole point of things that are
טרחא. tircha. That's when you say כל מה שבתוכו, kol ma shebetocho,
but as long as you don't say כל מה שבתוכו, kol ma
shebetocho, anything that is not attached, you take anything that is not
nailed down. I understand the millstone weighs a ton.
I understand. רבי אליעזר, Rebbi Eliezer, anyway, so this is the rule,
right? Things could be very heavy, they could be very much seen
as part of the house, if they're not nailed down, if they're
not attached, they don't go with it. And by the way, even
some things that are nailed down, like this case
of the mortar, if it was detached and then attached, it actually
says would not go with the house. רבי אליעזר אומר כל המחובר
לקרקע הרי הוא כקרקע. Rebbi Eliezer omer kol hamuchbar lekarka harei hu
kekarka. רבי אליעזר Rebbi Eliezer says, no, I'm sorry, that case about
the mortar, even though it started as detached, now it's attached and
now it's considered like the house itself. So this is going to
be the debate that we're going to focus on: something that started
detached, it wasn't dug straight into the wall or straight into the
ground, it started as a vessel detached, and then it was attached,
how much is it considered to be still a type of a
movable and how much is it considered to be something that is
fixed and attached to the ground? Okay, so he says that would
actually be considered attached. בזמן שאמר לו היא וכל מה שבתוכו, bizman
sheamar lo hi vechol ma shebetocho, if you say 'it and all
its contents', so הרי כולן מכורין, harei kulan mechurin, they're all sold.
בין כך ובין כך, bein kach uvein kach, even if you say
'all its contents', לא מכר לא את הבור ולא את הדות ולא
את היציע. lo machar lo et habor velo et hadut velo et
hayitzia. Going back to a previous משנה, even if you say the
contents, you're not going to sell the well or the cistern or
like the balcony because those things are not contents, those things are
structures themselves. So again, it's quite amazing, you've got this well in
the house itself, which is used for the water supply of the
house, and even if you say 'all of the contents', you're still
not selling the well, that's a separate structure. You want the well,
you pay separate for the well. Okay, so now we're going to
look at what really is going to be our focus, which is
this issue about something that was separate and then was attached. Now
you could say everything was separate and then attached unless I'm living
in a cave, right? Okay, but if you basically are building things
like stones and you're putting them together and you're building a house,
those don't exist as like a vessel, those are just building materials,
so that's clearly considered like מחובר לקרקע, muchbar lekarka, right, when you
build something. But if something exists separately and then it was nailed
down, okay, then the question is, is it still seen as like
this independent vessel that happens to be attached, or is it considered
to be part of the structure? Okay, and there's going to be
a lot of implications, you know, one is what do you sell
with the house, but we're obviously going to broaden it. So let's
take a look. This has a lot of very important relevance for
הלכה. halacha. תנו רבנן. tanu rabanan,
צינור שחקקו ובסוף קבעו. tzinor shechakako u'v'sof kava'o. You have a tube,
what's it called, a pipe that basically was carved out, so you've
got this pipe that was already made, like any normal pipe, you
build a, you go to the, you go to your hardware store,
you buy a pipe. It exists before it's attached. And then you
fixed it into the ground and you attached it to the ground.
And then you use that pipe to bring water into the מקווה.
mikvah. Now here's the thing, water that drawn water is פסול, pasul,
cannot be used for a מקווה, mikvah, but it has to be
straight rainwater. And if you think about how most מקוואות mikvahs are
sort of constructed, like they gather this water on the roof and
then it goes through this pipe into the מקווה. mikvah. So the
question is, okay, but let's say you're doing that, even if you
don't physically draw it, if the water goes through a vessel that
is considered a כלי, kli, a vessel in other הלכות, halachot, like
particularly in laws of טומאה, tumah, it could be it's susceptible for
becoming טמא. tamei. So the fact that it was in a vessel
even if it wasn't used, even if there was no human power
that actually drew it or moved it, that actually makes it considered
drawn water and invalid for the מקווה. mikvah. So the question is,
so then how does things like how does any water get brought?
So they basically, first of all, they use material that is not
מקבל טומאה, mekabel tumah, they use like this PVC pipe or whatever.
So that's one question, not all certain types of material. But the
other thing is, if that
if the thing does not have what is called, if it's metal,
it's a bigger problem because metal is can become טמא tamei even
like any type of metal vessel can become טמא. tamei. But if
it's not metal, it has to have what's called a בית קיבול,
beit kibul, something that is used as a receptacle. And a pipe,
although obviously water goes through it, it doesn't stay in it, right?
So the so therefore the only type of a pipe that is
considered a problem for מקווה mikvah purposes is at what it it
says that you חקקו לקבל
צרורות. chakako lekabel tzerorot. You've got this basic pipe and you made
a little thing here, so the water a trap, so the water
goes through and the stones fall down here. So in that type
of a pipe, because the stones get caught and don't just pass
through, it's considered a כלי kli and therefore it's a problem to
use that for a מקווה. mikvah. That's under every sink in America.
Is it? Okay. But if your pipe just looks for if your
pipe just looks like this and there's no human agency, it just
flows naturally, it's not a problem. Okay, but if it were like
this, it would be a problem. And why
would it be like that? To catch the stones. It goes like
this, it goes under every sink, the pipe goes like this, down,
oh, you mean the pipe itself goes like this?
But where ah, but that it does something like this so that
when you shave and all the hair okay, okay, fine. All right,
anyway, okay, so you have this pipe and this pipe has this
trap, so it's going to invalidate the מקווה. mikvah. But that's only
because it was a כלי, kli, a vessel, before it was attached.
If you dug this straight into the ground something like this, I
don't know how you would exactly do it, it would not be
a problem because it's only is considered a vessel if it was
detached from the ground. Now the point is it started detached and
now you've permanently affixed it to the ground. Does that make it
no longer considered a vessel and no longer a problem? So that's
exactly that's our conceptual question, okay? צינור שחקקו, tzinor shechakako, so you
first dug it out, you carved it, ובסוף קבעו, u'v'sof kava'o, then
you affixed it to the ground. פוסל את המקווה, posel et hamikvah,
that
invalidates, that's still considered to be a vessel even though now it's
attached. קבעו ובסוף חקקו, kavao u'v'sof chakako, let's say you took a
piece of a piece of
metal that was not yet carved out and you affixed that piece
of metal or whatever, not metal, I don't know, wood, you took
a piece of wood that was not yet carved out and you
affixed the wood to the ground, you like cemented it in, and
then you dug it out or maybe you're just digging out this
trap because it's only the trap that creates the problem. You affixed
this wood pipe first to the ground and then you dug out
the trap. So then it only became a vessel once it was
attached, which means it didn't become a vessel, okay? The basic concept
of a vessel is something that is not something that's מחובר לקרקע
mechubar l'karka halachically is not a vessel. So if it became a
vessel before it was מחובר לקרקע mechubar l'karka and then you attached
it, it would retain the status. But if you first attached a
piece of let's say wood pipe which was not yet a vessel
because it didn't have the trap, and after it was attached you
made the trap, then it never became a vessel because it was
because when it changed that way it was already part of the
ground. You have a question, Jenna? So חקקו chakako is specifically referring
to creating well,
it could be to carving the whole thing, but I'm trying to
give you in a more realistic scenario. It's pretty hard to carve.
whole pipe once the whole thing is attached to the ground. But
it's enough that it didn't have that trap, because without that trap,
it's not yet הלכתית halachically considered a vessel. So if you attached
even when the material is naturally found in the ground? Well no,
you took a piece of wood. Like I said, everything starts, not
everything, but whatever. Why don't we say a house isn't מחובר לקרקע
m'chubar l'karka because it started, you know, because you brought bricks to
create it. If it's just raw material that's attached then it is
considered מחובר לקרקע. m'chubar l'karka. It only becomes this question is when
you created a vessel unattached and then you attached it. So if
you took a piece of, you got yourself this nice, you know,
cylindrical piece of wood, not only a cylindrical piece of wood, a
tubing. And you took this whole wood tubing and you cemented it
to the ground, but then you carved out the trap. Since it's
that trap that makes it into a vessel, and when that happened
it was already attached to the ground, it's not considered a vessel.
But if you made that outside and then you attached it, then
it retains its status. Yes. Again, not a conceptual question. Am I
to understand from this that the way they made pipes was they
took a thick branch or a log and they hollowed it the
whole length of the thing out? That's the חקקו? chakeku? In other
words, to make to make a pipe, that's what they did? They
hollowed it out? It sounds like it. Yeah, yeah, that's exactly. But
I mean the Romans had lead pipe and they didn't do that.
They made pipes, but... Right. Okay, yeah, okay. Alright, so, I mean
how did the Romans make pipes? You mean they like poured molten
metal into some type of mold? No, how did they make pipes?
No, they had a sheet of lead and they rolled it, and
they rolled it essentially. Okay, well if it's metal then this whole
thing, you don't need the trap. Okay, so we're talking that it's
wood, okay. Alright. So צינור שחקקו ולבסוף קבעו tzinor shechakeku u'l'vasof kavao
פוסל את המקווה. posel es hamikvah. קבעו ולבסוף חקקו, kavao u'l'vasof chakeku,
okay, אינו פוסל את המקווה. aino posel es hamikvah.
So that's a question, when does something retain its status of a
כלי? kli? If it's a כלי kli before it's attached and then
it's attached, it retains its status. If it's not a כלי kli
before it's attached and then you made it into one, it doesn't
become one. I'll tell you another relevant question for this, I just
have to give this example,
which is so for like laws of נדה, niddah, another place it's
true, it's interesting, not on the מקווה mikvah side, on the נדה
niddah side. Another, one of the main areas in which laws of
טומאה tumah still are relevant today are in laws of נדה. niddah.
So one is like is it a vessel for this מים שאובים
mayim sheuvim question and the other is if there's a blood stain
on something that is מקבל טומאה, m'kabel tumah, it's a problem. Okay.
So the question is, well how do you,
what about a toilet? Because is a toilet, so that's that's a
vessel and then you attach it to the ground, it's חקקו ולבסוף
קבעו, chakeku u'l'vasof kavao, so does that considered a vessel or is
that considered something attached to the ground? So interestingly, something that is
made only for the purpose, the toilet isn't functional until it's attached,
okay. So something that is made only for the purpose of being
attached, actually is seen as a, that's not considered a vessel. Okay,
but this actually is a real debate, discussion that comes up in
these laws. But something that exists as a vessel like this pipe
before it's attached and then it's attached, that's where we're having the
discussion. Jenna, you had a question? Jenna, you had a question? I
was just thinking the problem is when you go to the bathroom
on an airplane. Oh, that's not attached to the ground, right, exactly.
So yeah. Also like
the chemical... Alright, alright, okay you got me. So we'll have that
discussion some other time. But I just wanted to point out how
relevant this is, a very relevant issue. Another area again with מקווה
mikvah is a question about that you're not allowed to be טובל
tovel when you're standing on a כלי, kli, okay. There might be
different reasons for it. So there were all these questions about ladders
that were made and then affixed to the wall of a מקווה,
mikvah, especially when they would go use a well as a מקווה,
mikvah, okay, and you want to hold on to the ladder for
safety. Is that considered טבילה על גבי כלים? tvilah al gabei keilim?
Because a ladder exists as a ladder before you affix it and
then you affix it. So these are like there's a lot of,
I know it seems that this is all very obscure, but this
is a lot of relevant הלכות halachos to this question of צינור
שחקקו ולבסוף קבעו tzinor shechakeku u'l'vasof kavao has a lot of important
relevance להלכה. l'halacha. Yes. Is standing on something that might be a
כלי kli while you in order to get to be able to
reach into the מקווה mikvah like on the steps, is it you're
not טובל? tovel? No, no, it's when you are immersing your own
body you can't be
yeah, yeah you can't be standing on a כלי. kli. Right. Okay.
תנו רבנן, rabanan. so let's take a look. So the גמרא Gemara
says like this. אינו פוסל, aino posel, מאן? man? לא רבי אליעזר
ולא רבנן. lo Rabi Eliezer v'lo rabanan. Who is the author of
this ברייתא braisa that distinguishes between whether it was a כלי kli
that was affixed or became a כלי kli only after it was
affixed? It's neither רבי אליעזר Rabi Eliezer or the רבנן. Rabbanan
So הי רבי אליעזר, hai Rabi Eliezer, which רבי אליעזר Rabi Eliezer
are you referring to? So now we're going to try to identify
this, the fact the anonymous voice of the גמרא Gemara said there's
a relevant רבי אליעזר Rabi Eliezer to this. Which רבי אליעזר? Rabi
Eliezer? רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer is relevant to this discussion. So we're
going to start with our ברייתא braisa we just quoted before about
selling the house. אילימא רבי אליעזר דבית, Ileima Rabbi Eliezer deBayis, by
the case of the house, רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer says once you've
attached like that mortar to the house, it's considered part of the
house. So it seems like רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer would say even
if it was a כלי kli and then attached, it becomes part
of the, you know, becomes מחובר, mechubar, becomes part of the ground,
part of the house. So the גמרא Gemara says, wait, that might
not be generalizable. דילמא היינו טעמא דרבי אליעזר סבר מוכר בעין יפה
מוכר ורבנן סברי מוכר בעין רעה מוכר. Dilma hainu ta'ama deRabbi Eliezer
savar mocher b'ayin yafa mocher veRabbanan savri mocher b'ayin ra'a mocher. Maybe
they're not debating a, you know, a general question of is something
considered to be attached or not attached, part of the ground or
not part of the ground. Maybe they all agree it's somewhere in
the middle or who knows, it's definitely not for other הלכות halachos
part of the ground. It definitely is part of the ground. But
within the question of buying and selling, how do you deal with
things in the grey category? Are the grey category, you know, the
stuff right, you know, they're somewhere on the boundary line, are those
things that you're going to assume are sold or not sold? בעין
רעה בעין יפה, B'ayin ra'a b'ayin yafa, you know, is somebody, you
assume somebody is generous or you assume somebody isn't generous. So you
can't generalize from discussions of buying and selling what something's objective halachic
status is. All that, you know, all that shows is that there's,
that's a question about, about like people's intent and how we assume,
you know, how, you know, how narrow or broadly is the package
of what you're selling. So that's not relevant
for a broader discussion. אלא רבי אליעזר דכוורת. Ella Rabbi Eliezer deKeveret.
It's the כוורת. keveret. It's רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer of the bee-hive.
דתנן, Detnan, we taught in the משנה. כוורת דבורים. Keveret devorim.
So you have a bee-hive, and apparently the assumption here was, was
this was a hive that was not naturally attached to a tree,
maybe you removed it from a tree, and now you have cemented
it and affixed it to the ground. That's at least, I don't
know if people do that, that's at least what the רשב"ם ותוספות
Rashbam veTosafos say we're talking about. רבי אליעזר אומר הרי הוא כקרקע.
Rabbi Eliezer omer harei hu k'karka. Now it's attached to the ground,
it's considered like ground, like, like, like, like this ground. What's the
relevance of that? If you wanted to sell somebody your bee-hive, you
that's now physically attached, you would sell it with like כסף שטר
וחזקה. kesef shtar v'chazaka. You wouldn't sell it with הגבהה hagbaha or
something like that, okay? It has normal status of ground. וכותבין עליו
פרוזבול, V'kosvin alav pruzbul, a פרוזבול pruzbul right, which is used to
make sure that the שמיטה shmita doesn't annul the loans. So you
have, I can only Jenna owes me a thousand dollars, I want
to make sure that that loan doesn't get annulled. I basically have
to write over my loan to בית דין, beis din, but it
only works if Jenna has some land in her name. Why? The
way the רשב"ם Rashbam explains it is, he says, because land is
something that's ready to be collected. So the fact that it's in
theory it would be easy for me to collect my loan allows
us to see it as to some degree it's already collected. And
therefore שמיטה shmita does not, is not as relevant to it. To
שמיטה shmita is only for like outstanding loans. Okay? So if Jenna
doesn't have any land to her name, but I need to protect
my loan, so one thing I can do is I can take
David aside and say, David, I'm now going to transfer to Jenna
a square inch of my property so that, so that will allow
me to then write a פרוזבול. pruzbul. But let's say Jenna doesn't
have land but she owns this bee-hive, okay? So that's considered to
be a piece of land, okay, because it's attached to the ground
and I'm allowed to write this פרוזבול. pruzbul. ואינה מקבלת טומאה, V'eina
mekabeles tumah, and this is sort of, this is the maybe the
most directly relevant for the מקווה mikvah case, it's does not, is
not susceptible to becoming טמא, tamei, which is a general way of
determining is it a כלי kli or not a כלי. kli. Something
that's considered part of the ground or attached to the ground, it
does not become טמא. tamei. במקומה. Bimkomah. Right. Even though it was
a distinct כלי kli beforehand. Exactly.
So this is just like our case of the צינור, tzinor, you
have this bee-hive that was not attached, you then cemented it to
the ground and now it's considered according to רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer
a piece of the ground. So that's why it's not, that's why
it's not רבי אליעזר. Rabbi Eliezer. Because רבי אליעזר, Rabbi Eliezer, like
this idea that if it was separate and attached, רבי אליעזר Rabbi
Eliezer seems to say once you attach it, it is fully part
of the ground. Okay. במקומה, Bimkomah, if in its place. Now what's
the word במקומה bimkomah means here, you know, the רשב"ם Rashbam discusses
that it means that if you were to actually like remove the
honey from it, then you know, then it would then, the honey
actually would be מקבל טומאה, mekabel tumah, that's a different discussion. והרודה
ממנה בשבת חייב חטאת. V'harodeh mimena b'Shabbos chayav chatas. And this is
perhaps the most shocking. If you remove the honey from it on
שבת, Shabbos, you have violated שבת Shabbos because you have detached something
from the ground. Now that's funny because it's not like, it's not
like the taking an apple off a tree, it's not growing from
the ground. So presumably it doesn't mean that you're חייב chayav because
of like קוצר, kotzer, which is to cut something growing, but it
might mean that it's like a case of like סותר, soter, that
you are, you know, destroying a structure. It's not so clear. That
is maybe the most sort of shocking idea. But it's תולש, toleish,
he says תולש. toleish. Yeah, but that's hard to understand because תולש
toleish doesn't apply if I, if תולש toleish applies to things that
are growing, right, not to things that are not growing from the
ground. So even if it's considered attached, to consider it growing from
the ground, but maybe that's what the גמרא Gemara will see where
it... וחכמים אומרים v'chachamim omrim and the sages say אינו כקרקע eino
k'karka ואין כותבין עליה פרוזבול v'ein kotvin aleha pruzbul ומקבלת טומאה במקומה
u'mekabeles tumah bimkomah והרודה ממנה בשבת פטור. v'harodeh mimenah b'Shabbos patur. And
the חכמים Chachamim say no, no, it's not considered part of the
ground, it would not be sold like land would be sold, you
can't use it for a פרוזבול, pruzbul, it is טמא, tamei, it
is a separate
vessel, and by שבת Shabbos you'd be exempt. So this seems to
be a... the fact that it cuts across so many different categories
seems to be that we're talking about a general conceptual question, something
that was a separate vessel and then attached, is it now still
considered a vessel or is it now considered part of the ground?
So the גמרא Gemara says, yeah, that seems to be pretty good.
So the גמרא Gemara says no, התם כדאמר רבי אלעזר טעמא. hasam
k'd'amar Rabbi Elazar ta'ama. No, no, no, that's not generalizable. It's true
it applies across categories, but you can't extend it beyond the one
case of the beehive, because by the case of the beehive we
have a special פסוק. pasuk. What פסוק pasuk do we have by
the case of the beehive?
דכתיב d'chsiv by יהונתן Yehonatan when they went to that war, right,
it says ויטבול אותה ביערת הדבש. vayitbol oso b'ya'aras hadvash. And he
dipped it into the יערת דבש, ya'aras dvash, which we are reading
the forest of honey. So it is saying that honey here is
considered to be like a tree, and therefore it's considered to be
therefore like connected to the ground and connected to the tree, and
it's a different status. Now, תוספות Tosafos says what we're really doing
at this stage is we're changing the cases, we're switching from a
separate beehive that was physically cemented to the ground and we're now
saying we're talking just about a natural beehive. And the actual חידוש
chiddush that we're saying here is that... so what's the חידוש? chiddush?
If you have a beehive growing from a tree, of course it's
considered connected to the ground. No, the question is what's the status
of the honey? Is the honey in the hive... it's all natural,
it's a completely different case, not relevant to our discussion... is the
honey in the hive considered attached to the ground or not? Because
that is a little bit different than you think about like an
apple growing from a tree, right? Honey is sort of being stored
in the hive, it's not growing from the hive. The hive was
made on the tree, it wasn't like growing from the tree. So
that's like a really interesting question, right? Is that considered for שבת...
Shabbos... so if you say now going back to what Dov said
before about תולש, tolesh, that if you remove honey from a hive,
it's like picking apples from a tree. To some degree you understand
that,
experiential, sort of understand that, it's connected, it's food from the tree,
but it's not growing from the tree. But
because this verse refers to it as like a forest of honey,
sort of sees the honey
as like connected to the tree. So that's this... what? יערה, ya'ara,
I mean that's clearly... I know it's not the פשט. pshat. I
know it's not the פשט. pshat.
The רשב"ם Rashbam says, the רשב"ם Rashbam says that that is the
key as the word יערה ya'ara here is forest. What does the
word in context, what does it mean? A forest, it means... I
thought יערה ya'ara here is like עירוי, eruy, like I thought it
was like the flow of honey. Oh really? The flow of honey.
That's why I always understood that פסוק. pasuk. Interesting. Anyway, but the
way it's being read here is like a forest of honey. So
the חידוש chiddush here is that the hive and the honey here,
which were like are considered to be... even the honey which is
in the hive is considered to be like קרקע. karka. Let's say
I was just going to... although it does say you're selling actually
the כוורת kaveres itself. But let's say I was going to just
go ahead and sell you just the honey in the hive. Would
you have to do an הגבהה hagbahah on the honey or could
we do it through כסף kesef or שטר? shtar? Is it considered
like קרקע, karka, right? So
that's how we're sort of shifting gears here and it's not relevant
for things that are not beehives and not honey. So the גמרא
Gemara says אלא רבי אליעזר דדף. ella Rabbi Eliezer d'daf. So it's
רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer of the דף. daf. No, I'm just kidding.
So it's רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer of the... what do you call
it? Of the shelf. Okay, and we taught in the משנה: דף
של נחתומים. daf shel nachtomin. You have a shelf of bakers. Okay,
either this is a shelf that they do to knead the dough,
it's some type of a shelf attached to the wall and they're
kneading the dough, or the רשב"ם Rashbam says maybe it's a shelf
that they attach on the outside to display their wares. Okay. But
whatever it is, it's some type of a shelf that's been built
into the wall. Now, we're assuming that a shelving exists as a
type of a כלי kli even before it's attached. You know, it's
like some type of a usable plank of wood or something, it
could be used, it's not just building material. And now we're going
to attach it to the wall. דף של נחתומים שקבעו בכותל, daf
shel nachtomin shekavo b'kosel, רבי אליעזר מטהר, Rabbi Eliezer mitaher, רבי אליעזר
Rabbi Eliezer says it is not susceptible for impurity even though it
was a presumably a vessel that's now attached, now that it's attached
it now is considered part of the structure, it's no longer a
vessel. וחכמים מטמאים, vachachamim metamin, and the חכמים chachamim say that it's
טמא. tamei. So presumably nobody cares whether it was first made into
a shelf and then attached, first attached and then made into a
shelf, רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer says the fact that it's now attached
means that it is part of the structure, it is not a
vessel. And the חכמים Chachamim say the fact that that it serves
as a vessel now, it is a vessel even though it's attached.
So מני? mani? So now who is? So neither רבי אליעזר Rabbi
Eliezer or חכמים Chachamim distinguish between whether it was first made and
then attached, or first attached and then made. So our case about
the about the pipe for the מקווה mikvah doesn't fit either of
those because our pipe case distinguishes between when it was made. So
אי רבי אליעזר, ee Rabbi Eliezer, if the pipe case was רבי
אליעזר, Rabbi Eliezer, אפילו חקקה ולבסוף קבעה, afillu chakakah l'vasof kava'ah, רבי
אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer then it should always be never be a problem
even if you made it a vessel and then attached it because
the case of the of the shelf seems to be even though
it was a shelf and then attached, it's for רבי אליעזר Rabbi
Eliezer it's okay. So רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer says it's never a
vessel, so then the pipe doesn't fit רבי אליעזר's Rabbi Eliezer case.
אי רבנן ee Rabbanan and if it's the Rabbis, אפילו קבעה ולבסוף
חקקה, afillu kava'ah l'vasof chakakah, the Rabbis seem to say it's always
considered a vessel even if it was first attached and then carved
out. So also the pipe case wouldn't fit. The pipe distinguishes between
was it first made and then attached or first attached and then
made. But this case of the shelf, right, there nobody is drawing
any distinctions. It seems like רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer always says it's
not a vessel and the Rabbis say it always is a vessel.
So that's what we meant when we said our case of the
pipe doesn't fit either רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer or the רבנן because
in this case we're not talking about beehive, we're talking about טומאה,
tumah, we're talking about a case that is directly relevant and they
don't seem to make any distinctions between whether you first made it
and then attached or first attached and then made, so this case
of the pipe that makes those distinctions, who is it going like?
That now we finally have focused in on our question. So let's
see what the גמרא's Gemara answer is.
So the גמרא Gemara says like this, לעולם רבי
אליעזר היא. l'olam Rabbi Eliezer hi. Really it's רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer
that's
that in the case of the of the shelf says it's always
okay. So why is the pipe, why so why is that
and why is the pipe you make these distinctions and not in
the case of the shelf? שאני פשוטי כלי עץ דטומאה דרבנן. pshani
pshutei k'lei eitz d'tumah d'rabbanan. Ah because the shelf isn't really טמא.
tamei. A shelf, think about a straight shelf of a place plank
of wood. So what did I tell you before about the pipe?
That something that is wood is only מקבל טומאה m'kabbel tumah if
it has what's called a בית קיבול, beit kibul, some type of
a receptacle. Well a flat shelf doesn't have a receptacle. So therefore
it's not really טמא. tamei. But the גמרא Gemara says that it
would at least be rabbinic. So this leads to a big discussion.
What do you mean rabbinic? We normally don't assume that there's this
middle ground. We normally assume that if it has a receptacle it's
susceptible for becoming טמא tamei and if it doesn't have then it's
completely not biblically or rabbinically. There's no middle state where it's a
problem rabbinically and not biblically. So this actually becomes a very important
גמרא because it leads to an understanding in the ראשונים Rishonim which
is something that is a quasi-receptacle.
A big flat surface that is used for supporting things functions as
a receptacle. It's not a receptacle in the fact that if you
put liquid on it or things that roll on it they won't
stay on it. But if you put other things they will stay
on it. So a tabletop surface or a shelf is rabbinically like
a receptacle. And that actually you know where that is relevant? Okay
I'm just going to prove to you how relevant הלכות טומאה וטהרה
Hilchos Tumah v'Taharah is. One other area where הלכות טומאה וטהרה Hilchos
Tumah v'Taharah very relevant is סכך sechach on a סוכה sukkah which
can't be by something that's מקבל טומאה. m'kabbel tumah. So everybody wants
to know can I go ahead and you know I don't know
go ahead and get some like planks some 2x4s right and put
them on the top of my סוכה. sukkah. Is that because it
doesn't have a receptacle? Okay now if it's like narrow or whatever
it's not made for supporting something but if you've got like a
big plank of wood that's actually like you know made to support
stuff there are times in which that even though there's no receptacle
would be טמא tamei because it's made as a base as a
to support things you know to for things to be support you
know placed on it and supported on it. Okay so that's anyway
so that's this case. So the גמרא says ah
that's rabbinic. Because it's only rabbinic רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer isn't distinguishing
between did you make it first and then attach it or attach
it and then make it. But something like this pipe with a
real receptacle this type of a thing that's when he would draw
a distinction between did you make it first and then attach it
or attach it and then make it. Yes Rabbi Dov. It's very
beautiful these פסוקים pesukim about the דבש devash in שמואל א. Shmuel
Aleph. There's two פסוקים. pesukim. ויבוא העם אל היער. vayavo ha-am el
ha-ya'ar. Right and the troops came into the forest. Right. The next
פסוק pasuk says ויונתן לא שמע בהשביע אביו את העם וישלח את
קצה המטה אשר בידו ויטבול אותה ביערת הדבש. v'Yonatan lo shama bahashvia
aviv et ha-am vayishlach et ktzeh hamateh asher b'yado vayitbol otah b'ya'arat
ha-devash. How do they translate יערת? ya'arat? Hive. Hive. So that's interesting.
Beautiful play right on hive and forest. Right. So into the forest
and then the פסוק pasuk is the דבש devash of the forest.
Right. Nice. Nice. Okay. So okay, good, great. So now let's just
finish this point. So he says, okay, so the reason here we
make a distinction between the order and by the case of the
of the shelf we don't is because the shelf is only rabbinic,
it's only this flat wooden thing, it's rabbinic so we can we're
going to be very lenient and say it'll never be a problem.
But here where it's a real vessel we're going to distinguish between
what was it first made and then attached or first attached and
then made. So the Gemara says מכלל דשאובה דאורייתא michlal de'sheuvah d'oraita
one minute. If you're saying here we're being stricter because it is
a biblical vessel
but okay but the whole category of drawn water for a mikveh
that's not biblical that's rabbinic. I'm going to get back to that
in a minute. So since this whole category is rabbinic, if Rabbi
Eliezer is always lenient when it's rabbinic regardless of the order, he
should have been lenient here too because because this whole category of
drawn water is a rabbinic category. והא קיימא לן דרבנן v'ha kayma
lan d'rabanan we hold that this category of drawn water for a
mikveh is a rabbinic category. And not only that, how about Rabbi
Yosei bar Rabbi Chanina? בדכתייא דמתכת מחלוקת b'dichtaya d'matachet machloket when we're
talking about that shelf by the baker, we're not talking about a
wooden shelf, we're talking about a metal shelf. But wood is also
מקבל טומאה. mekabel tumah. Metal is מקבל טומאה mekabel tumah without a
בית קיבול. beit kibul. Metal and therefore a metal shelf is biblically
a vessel. So therefore you can't say that we're being Rabbi Eliezer's
being lenient by the shelf because it's only rabbinic. First of all,
this is rabbinic as well. Second of all, the case of the
shelf is biblical because we're talking about a metal shelf and you
don't need to have a receptacle. So the Gemara says fine, flip
it. So the Gemara says לעולם רבנן היא. leolam rabanan hi. Fine,
it's the rabbis. The rabbis by the metal shelf say it's always
טמא tamei and they don't care about the order. You know why?
Because that's biblical. So they're being extra strict there or they're being
עיקר הדין ikar hadin there. And therefore whatever the order is, it's
always a vessel. But in this case which is rabbinic because the
whole law of drawn water is rabbinic, in this case they'll be
more lenient and they'll say if you first attached it and then
made it, it's not a vessel, if you first made it and
then attached it, it is a vessel. Okay, so basically what the
Gemara is saying is now there's a question who do we rule
like? According to Rabbi Eliezer, it'll never it doesn't matter what the
order is, once it's attached it's never a vessel. And according to
the חכמים chachamim in biblical matters presumably by the like the shelf,
order doesn't matter. But in rabbinic matters, if you first if you
first attached it and then make it, it's not a vessel, if
you first make it and then attach it it is. So there's
a big question how do we rule the הלכה halacha and then
what categories are biblical and what are rabbinic? Because as I said,
this is actually very relevant to a wide range of halachic matters.
Yes, in the mikveh for example, if you use metal piping
if you use metal piping, that'd be a problem without a בית
קיבול. beit kibul. Exactly, exactly. That's why we don't use metal piping.
Exactly, right. So now let's just read the last line. Stone could
be used. Stone, PVC, wood, right. Okay.
So the Gemara says אי הכי i hachi so the Gemara says
אפילו חקקו ולבסוף קבעו נמי ושאני התם דרבנן היא. afillu chakako ulevasof
kavo nami v'shani hatam d'rabanan hi. Here we're going to be lenient
and say that it's go since it's only rabbinic, here we'll say
it's not מקבל טומאה, mekabel tumah, it's not a problem if you
first attached it because it's all rabbinic. The Gemara says אי הכי
אפילו חקקו ולבסוף קבעו נמי. i hachi afillu chakako ulevasof kavo nami.
If that's true, if you're going to be lenient because the whole
thing is rabbinic, even if you first made the pipe and then
attached it why not be lenient? So the Gemara says no, שאני
התם דאיכא תורת כלי עליו בתלוש. shani hatam d'ika torat kli alav
b'talush. No no no, even though it's rabbinic, if the thing was
a vessel first and then attached later we're gonna keep it have
its status as a vessel. Okay, which is obviously the point we
were making. So the basic rule is does something lose its status?
You know, is it a vessel or not? According to Rabbi Eliezer,
even if you first made it and then attached it, it's no
longer a vessel. Now it's part of the ground. According to the
חכמים chachamim by biblical matters like the shelf, it's always a vessel.
Whereas by rabbinic matters, they'll say if it was first a vessel
and then it's attached it's still a vessel. If it was first
attached and then made, it's not. So it gets you know, you
have to sort of keep all the you know, all the different
positions there. Let me say one sentence about drawn water being rabbinic.
Does this really mean it? Does that really mean that I can
go ahead and go to my bathtub and turn on the you
know, turn it on and get all that drawn water there and
biblically speaking that's a kosher mikveh? So some ראשונים rishonim say yeah.
The whole problem, the whole reason we have all this stuff for
the mikvahs is all rabbinic. So biblically you can have drawn water.
And that they say well then why did the rabbis make that
up? Like what's their concern if it's all okay? So they say
no, the one thing that would not be okay biblically would be
to actually immerse in a vessel, like to get like a barrel
and to you know, so maybe that gets so the question of
About the question of is the bathtub a vessel is this question.
You had a bathtub and then you attached it to the ground,
so we could have that whole discussion. But let's say you had
a free-standing barrel that you filled with water and then you dunked
in it. That would not be good from the תורה. Torah. But
if you, what? Because they say it's מקוה מים Mikveh Mayim means
like somehow they they understand that the פסוק Pasuk means like it's,
I don't know, gathered in the ground. I'm not exactly sure what
the פשט Pshat is. No, מים חיים Mayim Chayim is different. מים
חיים Mayim Chayim is for זב Zav and it's for זב Zav
and that's natural flowing water. No, no, no, no, no. נדה, Niddah,
yes, but it's not מים חיים. Mayim Chayim. Okay? It's rainwater. But
anyway, one opinion is the only thing that biblically is not acceptable
is immersing in a vessel, but if the water is now in
the ground or something attached to the ground which sort of gets
to this question, then biblically speaking, you could basically draw water in
buckets and pour it in. It's all rabbinic. Others disagree and they
say, no, when the גמרא says here it's rabbinic, it means if
basically you first started with a kosher מקוה Mikvah and then added
drawn water or if it was partly filled and you added drawn
water, then it would be rabbinic. But if it's all drawn water,
then that would be biblical. So that becomes very interesting in terms
of like you know thinking about what we need to make a
kosher מקוה, Mikvah, how much of it might be biblical requirements and
how much of it might be
rabbinic. Okay, and then the last line that we read, it says
the top...